<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the improvement of time a sermon preach'd before the Queen at White-Hall, August 7, 1692 / by Edward Gee.</title>
            <author>Gee, Edward, 1657-1730.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G458</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23947</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07933411</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07933411</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40512</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42573)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40512)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1207:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the improvement of time a sermon preach'd before the Queen at White-Hall, August 7, 1692 / by Edward Gee.</title>
                  <author>Gee, Edward, 1657-1730.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Brab. Aylmer and Sam. Smith,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cover title: Mr. Gee's sermon before the Queen at White-Hall, August 7, 1692.</note>
                  <note>"By Her Majesties special command."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Ephesians V, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:40512:1"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>GEE</hi>'s SERMON Before the QUEEN AT WHITE-HALL, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 7. 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40512:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40512:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the Improvement of Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the QUEEN AT WHITE-HALL, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 7. 1692.</p>
            <p>By EDWARD GEE, Rector of St. <hi>Benedict</hi> by <hi>Paul's-Wharff,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to Their Majeſties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Her Majeſties Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Brab. Aylmer</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> and <hi>Sam. Smith</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:40512:3"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40512:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the QUEEN.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Epheſians V.</hi> Verſ. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Redeeming the Time, becauſe the days are Evil.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ST. <hi>Paul</hi> in this Epiſtle having ſhewn them to whom it was ſent, the Great Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the Chriſtian Religion, and the mighty Advantages and Privileges that might be received from the hearty belief of it; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to ſhew what a wonderful Change had been made in their Condition by embracing the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt; That whereas before their knowing and believing that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrin, they were covered with Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and altogether loſt in Vanity and Error, and might be ſaid to be even <hi>dead in Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40512:4"/>and Sins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.1.</note> They were now become Children of Light, by being the Children of God, their Minds were enlighten'd, and themſelves <hi>quickened,</hi>
               <note place="margin">—5.</note> and raiſed as it were from the dead <hi>to ſit together in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">—6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus laid down the mighty Things which had been done for them, Our Apoſtle does very eaſily and very regularly too, paſs on to inform them, what <hi>They</hi> alſo were to do, and what returns <hi>They</hi> were to make to God for ſuch his abundant Mercy to them. Upon this he gives them a great many Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Rules for the Management of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo as to pleaſe God in every Condition and ſtate of Life whatſoever, whether of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried or Free, whether of Publick or Private, of Son or of Servant; but above all he takes heed to mind them of their Care of <hi>That,</hi> in which all theſe things were to be done, all the Duties he mentioned were to be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and that is, the Good Improvement of their Time, that they would loſe none of that, ſince they had ſuch occaſion for it all, and yet were in ſuch apparent Danger of loſing too much of it, through the Wickedneſs of the World they muſt Converſe with; <hi>Redeeming the Time, becauſe the days are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:40512:4"/>
            <p>Which Words afford us theſe things for our Conſideration,</p>
            <p n="1">1<hi rend="sup">ſt.</hi> What great Reaſon we have all to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and to make a good uſe of our Time.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly.</hi> How much more Reaſon we have to Redeem it, and to double our Diligence, when we have loſt any great ſhare of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly.</hi> To inquire what can be the Hindrances of our Care in a Matter of ſo much moment.</p>
            <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">ly.</hi> To give ſome Rules herein, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort to the Practice of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1<hi rend="sup">ſt.</hi> What great Reaſon we all have to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, and to make a good Uſe of our Time.</p>
            <p>One would think it the moſt eaſie thing in the World to convince Mankind of the Truth hereof; but I know not well how it comes to paſs that this, which might challenge our Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent upon the very naming of it, <hi>That every Man ought to make the beſt uſe of Time,</hi> ſhould be ſo little regarded by the far greateſt part of the World; and nothing can be more ſtrange than this, that while all the World, the Wiſe and the Fooliſh are agreed in their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40512:5"/>valuing ſo much thoſe things which they love and take delight in, They ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in having little or no regard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which only they can obtain any of thoſe things they ſo much prize and long after.</p>
            <p>However, every Man muſt acknowledge the very great Reaſon there is for us all to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and to make a good Uſe of Time, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he is ſerious, or would but conſider theſe things with me,</p>
            <p n="1">1<hi rend="sup">ſt.</hi> How great a Work every Chriſtian has upon his Hands to perform.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly.</hi> How many Impediments He will meet with in his diſcharge of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly.</hi> How ſhort the time of our Sojourning here in this World muſt be. And</p>
            <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">ly.</hi> How much ſhorter the Miſpending of our Time does generally make it.</p>
            <p n="1">1<hi rend="sup">ſt.</hi> How Great a Work every Chriſtian has upon his Hands to perform.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:40512:5"/>
            <p>Indeed if One were to judge of the Buſineſs of too many Chriſtians by their Behaviour, one would be able to make but a very indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Judgment concerning it. To behold the Courſe of the World, would tempt a Man to believe that neither Reaſon nor Religion were regarded by the far greateſt part in it: to ſee ſome as unactive and idle, as if they had no more to do than the Flower in the Garden, or the Graſs upon the Ground, had nothing to do but to receive Nouriſhment, and grow; To ſee others Sotting away their Time, haunting the Publick Houſes conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, and diſtinguiſhing their whole Time into but three parts, the firſt of which they ſpend in Sleeping, the ſecond in Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the third and greateſt in Drinking; to ſee them minding nothing but what is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant and unmanly, loving no Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures but what are unlawful, giving their Strength to ſtrange Women, their Ears, their Eyes, and all their Senſes up to thoſe Charms, which are often Bitterneſs in the Taſte it ſelf, but moſt certainly Shame and Deſtruction at the laſt: To ſee ſome from whom one might expect a better Senſe of Religion, reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and turning every Stone, trying every way to be Rich, and minding nothing elſe but to leave a great Eſtate, and reſolved to do
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40512:6"/>it, though at the Expence of Religion and Conſcience, of Honour and of Juſtice, though they muſt diſregard the Tears as well as the Rights of Widows and Orphans, and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon the Helpleſs and Afflicted to come at thoſe Eſtates they have already ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their Deſire: To ſee others Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all they have in this World to Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Proſtituting their Virtue and Honour, Flattering and uſing the worſt of Men, if they will but give a lift towards that Height they are gazing at, and preferring Greatneſs, though it prove never ſo ſhort-liv'd, to all the Virtue, and Honour, and Conſcience in the World. To ſee theſe and a great many other, as ridiculous Scenes of Humane Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Behaviour here, too tedious to be mentioned or minded, muſt make one to conclude, either that Mankind are but a ſort of Animals devoid of Reaſon, that excel the Serpent and the Ape only in a little Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as they excel the reſt of their Fellow-Creatures, or that there is no God in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and they may do whatever is right in their own Eyes, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did when they had no King, on Earth, or that they are for ſuch their Behaviour inexcuſable Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40512:6"/>
            <p>And Mad-men they are, ſince how buſie ſoever they are about all theſe things, this was not their Buſineſs into this World; and how much ſoever they may have pleas'd themſelves in their ſeveral Actions, yet God can never be pleaſed with them, ſince it was for another, a more noble Purpoſe, that He Created Man upon the Face of this Earth: He planted us here, as in a place of Tryal, He appointed us a Work, which is no leſs than to purchaſe a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Immortality for our Bodies as well as our Souls in his Kingdom of Heaven, by our leading Lives of Piety and Virtue here. This is our chief Buſineſs into this World, and the Care of it ought to be conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our Eye, not only for the Worth, but alſo for the Difficulty of it: It is a difficult Work indeed, but were it Ten Thouſand times more difficult than it is, there is a Reward that would deſerve it all: But God has been infinitely gracious to us in this Reſpect, has been far from making the Difficulty equal to the Greatneſs of this bleſſed Reward.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:40512:7"/>
            <p>This however ought always to affect us, that it is a great and large Work, and this every one does know that has made never ſo little Progreſs in it: How much Study and Diligence is neceſſary to obtain, and to preſerve a juſt Knowledge of God and his Attributes, and of that wonderful Diſpenſation towards the Sons of Men by his own ever bleſſed Son? To preſerve our Faith pure and undefil'd from the Arts of Hereticks, and others that are ſtill laying wait to deceive with their enticing Words? To have our Judgments rightly informed, and firmly ſettled as to Matters of Faith and Knowledge, and the whole Nature of our Chriſtian Duty? How difficult a Task does it prove to incline the Will, and ſubdue it to the Obedience of Reaſon and Religion, to keep it even and conſtant to the Choice of real Good, and our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Duty? What a ſevere and laſting Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict muſt we have with thoſe Corrupt Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, thoſe unruly Deſires, and inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Paſſions that are always hanging a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us, and ready to betray us upon every Occaſion, upon the leaſt Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that preſents it ſelf? Theſe muſt all (in order to that Life which God requires
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40512:7"/>of us) be mortified, and reſtrain'd, and if we can, perfectly ſubdued.</p>
            <p>We have not only a great many Virtues to learn and practiſe, but a great many Vices to unlearn, which we muſt thank our own Folly for. We have not only Vices that muſt be parted with, but too many among us great habits of them, and what Time, and Pains, and Diligence are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the curing our Selves of any one ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of Wickedneſs! It was with ſome Care and Regret that we did bring our ſelves to venture on ſuch or ſuch a Waſting Sin, it was with more Pains and Diligence that we brought our ſelves to commit it with Greedineſs, and a particular Pleaſure in it: and can all this be undone and changed in a Moment, and when we have a mind? It muſt be with far more Pains, and Care, and Diligence, that we can tear it from our Breaſt, abandon, and quite forſake it, and not only forſake it, but frame our Mind, our Will, and our Temper, to that Virtue which is ſo contrary to it. One brisk Onſet cannot do our Buſineſs herein; we may with Courage and Reſolution ſet upon theſe Home-bred Enemies, and over-come them; but how long muſt it be before we can rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40512:8"/>our ſelves truly Conquerors over our fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Luſts?</p>
            <p>What a large Field then is that of the Knowledge, which is neceſſary as we are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, how many are the Snares and the Sins that we muſt (upon our greateſt Peril) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void and preſerve our ſelves unſpotted from? Have we then all of us ſo great, and ſo very large a Work as this is to perform? What Time can be enough for it? Bleſſed God! What Knowledge and Skill, and Diligence and Application, is neceſſary for the knowing and performing this our Duty, what Time can be too much for ſuch Buſineſs? And yet Mankind muſt certainly think its far from requiring all our Time, ſince they commonly do ſpend ſo much of it on quite other Matters. It was that Great Father of the Phyſicians Advice or Complaint, <hi>That Life was ſhort, but Art long,</hi> that Men had a great deal to learn, but too little time to acquire it in; how much more Reaſon has the Chriſtian to cry out, that his Work is great, but his Life too ſhort for it? and yet how many of us do ſquander away even that which we have.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40512:8"/>
            <p>There is too much of our precious Time forc'd away from us by the Neceſſities of our Nature, or our Relation and Care of others, how can we then find in our Heart to throw the reſt away after it? Is not the Race mark'd out for us, is not our Task allotted, and the time it muſt be done in, while it is Light? Let us then but inquire at home, and ſee how we have manag'd our Selves or our Time; if our Life be ſo ſhort, and our Work ſo great, have we employ'd it all therein? Is ſo much knowledge of God and his Laws ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to our ever being Happy, and have we made it our conſtant Care to ſtudy God's Word, to conſult thoſe Lips that ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Knowledge, and uſed all the Helps that might direct us in this? Are there ſo many Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues that God would have us Adorn our ſelves with, and ſo many Errors that we muſt aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and guard our Heart and our Life againſt with all Diligence, how much Time then have we employ'd to gain the one, or baniſh the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Let us ask our own Hearts what one Virtue it is we are entirely in Poſſeſſion of, what one Vice it is, that we have perfectly rid our Selves of? Has all the Time we have employ'd, as we ought, not made us Maſter of any one Virtue, nor ſo much as Conqueror over any one Vice, and can we think we have enough of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40512:9"/>Time, and to ſpare, which we may employ as our ſelves pleaſe? If all the Time that ſome of us have been in this World, (and how much has that been!) has not yet taught them one line, as I may ſay, of this large Leſſon, what time, how many hundreds of Years would be neceſſary to teach ſuch their whole Duty in?</p>
            <p>This Conſideration therefore ſhould awaken us all, ſhould prompt us to Diligence and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry in our Chriſtian Duty, ſince there is no Danger of our Times being too long for the Learning and Practice of our Duty, but too much Reaſon to fear that it may prove too ſhort; eſpecially if we remember the ſecond Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for this our Care, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly.</hi> How many Impediments He will meet with in his diſcharge of it.</p>
            <p>If our Task be large enough for our whole Time, as I have already proved, what Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions ſhould it cauſe in us to conſider how much of that Time (which was all but neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and little enough) is raviſhed from us by our neceſſary Occaſions, how much more is ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from it by our Sins and our Folly? Our Life is very fitly called in Scripture a Warfare, ſince if we look about us, and conſider how
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40512:9"/>much we have to do, and what great Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties we have to ſtruggle through, it would make the ſtouteſt Heart to Deſpond, but for the Grace of God, that will ſtrengthen and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt us, but for the Reward that will ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Crown us after our Succeſs in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts we ſhall be engag'd in here below.</p>
            <p>God has not been ſo liberal to us in the Term of our Lives, that we ſhould be ſo laviſh, and ſquander away ſuch large Portions of it. What a great ſhare of our Time does Neceſſity force from us? Our Sleep does almoſt cut our Life in two, and take an equal part; the ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe daily returning Wants of Food and Nouriſhment does take up at leaſt a third part of what remains; and for the reſt, how much does lawful Recreation take for its ſhare, how much does want of Health, or the Care of a weak and uneven ſtate of Health take alſo for its certain part? After ſuch a Diviſion one would think little could be left for worldly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, and none at all for other Matters, and yet we ſee how much of their Time does the Buſineſs and Employments of Mankind require, how much Care, and Time, and Diligence, is neceſſary to procure but a tolerable Subſiſtance for the far greateſt part in the World: Indeed this Time is all ſpar'd to them who have theſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40512:10"/>things left to their Hands, that are born to large Eſtates, and have no occaſion to ſpend any of their Time this way; but then alas, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſhews us, that too many of theſe who have ſo much more Time to ſpare than others, do generally make the leaſt and worſt Uſe of it. Not only our own Affairs, but thoſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and of Friends, nay, of meer Strangers, ſwallow up great part of our Time, and would ſpend us more of it, if Nature and Neceſſity would but give leave.</p>
            <p>Let us then compute our Time, and ſee what can remain, when Sleep and Nouriſhment, and Recreation and Health, and Buſineſs, have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried off ſuch large Shares, have we ſuch a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Portion left for that our Great Work, for the taking Care of our Laſt and Greateſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern? Would we but reflect a while on this account, it would make us bluſh, and be hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily aſham'd for all the Time we have ever miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in Sin and Folly; for theſe alas, crowd into the account of Impediments, and make too too great a Figure there, though we want no ſuch Hindrances. One would think Men could have no leaſure for the Service of theſe, that their manifold Buſineſs would have kept them always out of harms way, if we did not, to our Sorrow ſee, that though Men do ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40512:10"/>complain that their Buſineſs takes up their whole Time, that they can get no part of the day to employ as they willingly ſhould, and own they ought, in Holy Duties, yet that they can and will rob their Buſineſs to ſpend upon their Luſts and Pleaſures; That they will bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for a Boon Companion, for a Wanton Harlot, or a Drunken Club, though they will not for Religious Matters, Reading good Books, or to dedicate it either to the Publick or Private Worſhip of their God.</p>
            <p>Are not theſe then Hindrances big enough in our Great Work, which our Neceſſities and our Buſineſs give us? What muſt we ſay then when Wickedneſs comes in for a ſhare, and robs us moſt of all, when it's content with no mean ſhare, but inſinuates more and more, till all other Care is quite laid aſide, and it engroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes our whole Time? Should not this perſuade us, ſhould it not teach us, that ſince the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is really ſo great for which we were brought into this World, and the Time ſo uncertain, that we have to finiſh it in; that want of Time will not paſs for Excuſe in the other World, when our Sins and our Luſts have ſquander'd ſo much of it here; that ſince God has ſo form'd our Nature and our Tempers, that a great part of our Time muſt certainly be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40512:11"/>in the Care of theſe, and a great deal more of it may be ſnatch'd from us by Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or uncertain Health; we ſhould never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to employ well that Time which we can only call our own, to emprove all thoſe Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and Opportunities which God vouchſafes, and Time does reach out to us, to all the great and good Purpoſes for which our Lord did place us here.</p>
            <p>But alas, we forget all this, we do not only forget that our Work is ſo great, and that the Impediments we meet with in this our Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney are ſo many, but which is altogether as unhappy, we forget in the Third place,</p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly.</hi> How ſhort the Time of our Sojourning here in this World muſt be.</p>
            <p>It has been an old and a great Complaint of the Shortneſs of Humane Life, and if when the Lives of Men were far longer than they now are, and they had lived twice as long as the Generality of the World now does, they could complain that their days <hi>had been few:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 47.9.</note> We muſt not wonder at any Complaints we hear now. Our Life is fitly compar'd in Gods Word to the Graſs of the Field, to the more tender Flower, which though it is ſometime in grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40512:11"/>up, yet ſoon fades, is withered and gone; and as if this was not ſufficient to Convince us of the Shortneſs and Vanity of our Lives, the Scripture has thought fit to deſcend, and make even a Vapour and a Shadow the Emblems of our ſhort and fading Time, and to uſe them often as the fitteſt Emblems to expreſs it by. <hi>Job</hi>'s Friend pleads this in excuſe for his Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and it will ſerve for the reſt of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, <hi>Job</hi> 8.9. <hi>For we are but of Yeſterday, and know nothing, becauſe our days upon Earth are a Shadow:</hi> And <hi>Job</hi> himſelf concludes this as the common Lot to us all, that we are but of few days, and which is more Unhappy, that they are full of Trouble; That <hi>Man cometh forth</hi> [indeed] <hi>like a Flower, but is cut down;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 14.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>that he fleeth alſo as a Shadow, and continues not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the ſame Senſe have the wiſer part of the Heathen World had of the Condition of Mankind, that his Life is very ſhort, too ſhort in their Opinion for ſo Noble and ſo Wiſe a Creature: They have compar'd it to a meer Point, and indeed, what is the longeſt Life more to the days of Eternity? They have laught at the dividing this little Point into ſo many parts, but moſt of all at Mankind, for miſimploying any part thereof. And does it not appear the ſame to us all? As for the Time paſt, for all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40512:12"/>the Years we have lived hitherto, how wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſhort and inconſiderable does it appear to us? How little a Time is it, think we all, ſince we were Children, ſince we came abroad into the World? It's all gone as ſwiftly as a Shadow, and is vaniſh'd as if it had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally but a Vapour. The Time preſent of our Life, which is all that we can juſtly call the time of Life, how fleeting and uncertain is it alſo, and how haſty to be gone? How little will it ſtay for us? It does not wait our lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, nor can attend till we'll be pleaſed to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it to its juſt and proper uſe: We may call it our own indeed, and it's all we can call ſo; but then it will not for all that be at our Command, there is another Lord over it as well as us, that will not let it wait for us, nor ſtay for our Appointments. And if our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time of Life be ſo very little in our Power, what ſhall we ſay concerning that part of it, which is not yet in View, but wholly in the Hands of God, and known only to him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ſhall ſee it ever at all? This is the State of Human Life, and can this deſerve to be thought otherwiſe of than as very ſhort and very uncertain? We get through indeed a great many Months and Years, ſome a very great many; but then, if we take a Stand and look back, it appears nothing, is as inviſible as the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40512:12"/>Morrow to us all, as the day that is not yet in Being.</p>
            <p>This is God's fatal and irreverſible Decree upon us; it is not only appointed for us all to Die, but to die ſoon, after a few years of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and Sorrow here: We begin the World as if we knew all this before we came out of the Womb; we Lament betimes as it were our hard Fate, that we muſt live ſo few Years here, and thoſe too not Happily: As ſoon as we are born, we draw to our End, and ſome indeed do end as ſoon as they have begun; they enter the Stage of this World indeed, but like Mutes, they have no other part there but to be Seen, and then immediately are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried off; ſome ſtay longer indeed upon it, but there are too few that ſtay out the laſt Scene; their Generation is haſtned off to make room for the next that is to come, and ſo the World does very quickly change all its Inhabitants, and in a ſhort ſpace of Years, ſhews a perfectly new Set of Faces there.</p>
            <p>Are all things then in ſuch a changing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition? Is it ſo diminutive a part of Time that we are ſuffer'd to ſtay here before our Great Change? And is our Life it ſelf ſo much ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40512:13"/>in Compariſon, and ſo uncertain, that when we are going to Sleep, the Cunningeſt Man ith' World cannot aſſure us that we ſhall wake in this Life any more; that after we are riſen, we ſhall ever come into a Bed to take our Reſt again? Are all things, I ſay, in ſuch a condition with us, and can we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give our ſelves the miſpending all our preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Time, or too great a ſhare of it? May we be beckon'd out, or juſtled off our preſent Station ſo very ſoon, and can we find in our Hearts to have done nothing that became us either as Men or Chriſtians? Have we but one day of Life to do all our mighty Buſineſs in, and can we afford to ſtand it all out idle and gazing? This is Folly indeed, and what God will never forgive us, tho we are ſo over-kind to our ſelves. Our Life ſpends as faſt, and our Hours run off as ſwiftly while we are loytering and gazing about us, as when we are diligent at our proper Work.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore, ſince we are certain to have but little of Time allotted to our ſhare, be careful to ſpend all that little well; let not Buſineſs, or Diverſion, or Friends, rob us too much, or ſpend too much of our ſmall Stock; but let us rather borrow from each of them all the Time we can to Dedicate to the Glory
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40512:13"/>of our Great God, and to the Saving of our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls: But above all, let us not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Sinful Pleaſures to rob us alſo. If we do not keep directly on in our way without faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards our Journey's end, let us not for God's ſake loſe our ſelves ſo far as to turn quite back, and go directly from it; if we ſcarce have Time or Strength to perform this our Courſe once, let's not think of running it all twice over without Strength or Time. We have no continuing City here below, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to another, which we muſt make all our way to get to with what ſpeed we can, ſince we have but one Day to do it in, and when the Night comes, we are ſure to be wildred and loſt and quite excluded.</p>
            <p>But further, we are not only to conſider how great our Work is, how many the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments are, and how ſhort our Time to do all in muſt be, but this alſo ſhould add very much to our Care to reflect,</p>
            <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">ly.</hi> How much ſhorter the Miſpending of our Time does generally make it.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:40512:14"/>
            <p>In their worldly Affairs Men do always con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the not Employing that Time to their chief Buſineſs for which it was allotted, is generally a direct Miſpending of it, though it ſhould not be quite loſt, but employ'd about Things that are of leſs Concern: This is their Judgment about the Matters that concern this World, that concern their Health or Eſtate here; but it is not in thoſe Spiritual Affairs, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Soul and another State; they can with Patience enough ſuffer the Time allotted to theſe Beſt Things to be raviſhed from them, without Noiſe, or any of the Paſſion with which they are ſo Loud, when they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted in their other Affairs: It too often proves a Grateful Diverſion to be diſturb'd in their Care of theſe, and they can be ſo good-natur'd as not only to forgive others their taking from them that their ſet Time for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Duties, but to forgive themſelves as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily, when they neglect them, even upon the moſt frivolous Pretences. But theſe Men real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are too too much good-natur'd, and it were Happy for them if they had a great deal leſs of this which they call Good Nature, and a great deal more of that, which the World will call Moroſe Incivility: It would really be much better, and much more Happy for them by a little of <hi>This</hi> to ſecure and reſcue that Time
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40512:14"/>wherein they might make themſelves everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly Bleſſed, than by the help of <hi>the Other</hi> to loſe their Time, and their Soul together.</p>
            <p>This is a Concern wherein the leaſt loſs is very dangerous, ſince the Stake is ſo very great, and therefore no Care of ours can be too great for it. We do not only loſe all that our Time that is Miſpent on other things than that of our great Concern in this Life, but our Miſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing does too often prey upon our Time it ſelf, and cut that ſhorter: The Time we ſquander away in idle Speculations, or in things that are not directly Sinful, will, whenever we come to our ſelves, be a Grief of Heart unto us, ſince we ſhall then find and know, that we had a far better Uſe to have employ'd it to: But with what Heart ſhall we behold our ſelves, when we find that all the Time we have ſpent in Sin, did directly tend to the ſhortening of our days, as it ever moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly did. There are none of thoſe Sinful Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and Drunken Bouts, there is no Revel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, nor Wantonneſs, but coſts the Man that is employ'd therein, too much of his Life, and often all that is remaining of it. Without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Phyſician, every one can ſee how often Dropſy and Gout are the Fruits of Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Conſumption and Palſy, and Diſeaſes not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40512:15"/>fit to be nam'd, are the certain Effects of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful and Unchaſt Pleaſures: Need any Man be told, that theſe cut ſhort the Life of Man? The Sinner himſelf needs it leaſt of all, who feels to his too great Coſt, and by dear Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, the diſmal Truth of it; The Life that's cark'd with anxious Cares for the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Wealth, that will ſee no end, nor dare to taſte the Fruit of all its Care, but ventures Health, and Friends, and Life it ſelf, and which is more, all his future Hopes for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other bag, is far from ſcaping free on this Account: And there is no other Vice that Men allow themſelves in, which has not this Skill, and never fails, to ſhorten the Lives of thoſe that are ſo blindly fond of it. But if theſe Sinners ſhould be ſo Diſcreet in their Folly, and Temperate as it were in theſe their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies, as not to haſten too ſoon their End by them, yet this can give them but ſmall Comfort, ſince God may be provok'd by their Sins, ſo far as to cut off their Days, and ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten (as he often has done) the Lives of all ſuch careleſs and bold Sinners: And this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration ought to be well weighed by them all, who are ſo daring againſt God; for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Care may do for them againſt their own, or other Mens Vices, it can do nothing for them againſt the Vengeance of an Offended
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40512:15"/>God, which can never miſs its aim, or return again empty without accompliſhing that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon Careleſs and Wicked Men which God has appointed it. And how often has he appointed and declar'd, that they who make the worſt uſe of Time, ſhall have the leaſt ſhare of it to Miſpend; that he will cut off half the days of the Wicked, and haſten them off the Stage of this World to Judgment, who of all Men Living are the leaſt prepar'd for it? It is Employing our Time well, and the Fear of our God that will prolong our days, but for the Years of the <hi>Wicked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 10.27.</note> He has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd, <hi>That they ſhall be ſhorten'd. The Candle of the Wicked is often</hi> ſoon <hi>put out;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 21.17.</note> and when Men begin too ſoon, when they ſet up for Atheiſtical Debauchees in the Bloom of their Years, God's Judgment can be as quick with them, and not only ſhorten the days of their Youth it ſelf, but cover them (and their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory alſo) with Shame and Diſgrace.</p>
            <p>Having now gone through all the Reaſons I did believe ſufficient in this Matter, it is Time to take a ſhort View of them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to ſee what urgent and unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Neceſſity they lay upon us to be very ſtrict in the Improvement of our Time, ſince it is by the Benefit of this alone that we can
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40512:16"/>do any part of our greateſt Work in this World. Can we ſuffer our ſelves to be ruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Idleneſs, or worn out in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Sin and Luſts, who have no leſs a Work on our Hands than the gaining Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? Let us up and be doing, ſince if we Faint, we ſhall get nothing but what we ſhall for ever after wiſh we had eſcaped; but if we Faint not, we ſhall be ſecure of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great Reward, which will infinitely ſurpaſs all the Pains that we can ever take to obtain it.</p>
            <p>We know that our Work is great, we ſee that our Hindrances and Impediments are too many, and we cannot but feel, that the Time of our Sojourning here muſt not be long. What Time can we have for the Service of Sin, who have not enough for our lawful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, but eſpecially for our greateſt Work? And yet we can rob from theſe to ſpend upon our Luſts, which do not only Miſpend, but ſhorten our Time, which do not only give us nothing for it, but do moſt wickedly rob us alſo of <hi>That</hi> wherein we might have made ſome amends to God for our paſt Follies. But above all, let us look up to the Judgment, which is ſo like to overtake us in our Sin, and cut off our Life for our Wickedneſs, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40512:16"/>oftentimes in the very Act of it. Awake then, O thou who ſleepeſt, Awake to Righteouſneſs, and give thy Strength and thy Time to God; let him only have the continual Service of it, who will ſo abundantly reward it.</p>
            <p>I cannot enter upon the next Particular, which was to ſhew, <hi>How much more Reaſon we have to Redeem our Time, and to double our Diligence, when we have loſt any great ſhare of it.</hi> I have already treſpaſt on your Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence too far, and I hope I need add no more to Convince us how great a Concern we all ought to have for our Precious Time; if what I have already ſaid does not, I deſpair of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to urge any thing further that can teach us this Wiſe Leſſon. Let us Reflect then with Care on all theſe Reaſons, and ſince ſo much of Time ſlips from us Uſeleſs, let us be careful of the reſt, that while it is called Day, and we have Time, we may be employ'd about our Maſter's Buſineſs, and when he calls us hence, we may be found at it. But for all that Time which we have loſt, and is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverably gone, Let us go to the Bleſſed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that moſt Merciful Saviour, Let us caſt our ſelves at his Feet, and with Contrite Hearts bewail the Loſs and the Abuſe of our paſt Time, and beg of Him, that He would paſs
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40512:17"/>over the Follies of our Child-hood, that He would not remember the Sins of our Youth, nor the more grievous Tranſgreſſions of our Riper Years, but would Forgive us all that is paſt, and grant us his Grace, that we may all of us henceforth Serve and Pleaſe Him in Newneſs of Life, to His Glory, and our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
